beginners course my name is moon shot 1
omelette and I will be your instructor
for this course I'm a DevOps and cloud
trainer at code cloud comm which is an
interactive hands-on online learning
platform I've been working in the
industry as a consultant for over
thirteen years and have helped hundreds
of thousands of students learn
technology in a fun and interactive way
in this course you will learn docker
through a series of lectures that use
animation illustration and some fun
analogies that simplify complex concepts
we have demos that will show you how to
install and get started with docker and
most importantly we have hands-on labs
that you can access right in your
browser I will explain more about it in
a bit but first let's look at the
objectives of this course in this course
we first try to understand what
containers are what docker is and why
you might need it and what it can do for
you we will see how to run a docker
container how to build your own docker
image we will see networking in docker
and how to use docker compose what
docker registry is how to deploy your
own private registry and we then look at
some of these concepts in debt and we
try to understand how docker really
works under the hood we look at docker
for Windows and Mac before finally
getting a basic introduction to
container orchestration tools like dr.
Swann and kubernetes here's a quick note
about hands-on labs first of all to
complete this course you don't have to
set up your own labs well you may set it
up if you wish to if you wish to have
your own environment and we have a demo
as well but as part of this course we
provide real labs that you can access
right in your browser anywhere anytime
and as many times as you want
the labs give you instant access to a
terminal to a docker host and an
accompanying quiz portal the quiz portal
asks a set of
questions such as exploring the
environment and gathering information or
you might be asked to perform an action
such as run docker container the quiz
portal then validates your work and
gives you feedback instantly every
lecture in this course is accompanied by
such challenging interactive quizzes
that makes learning docker a fun
activity so I hope you're as thrilled as
I am to get started so let us begin
[Music]
we're going to start by looking at a
high-level overview on why you need
docker and what it can do for you let me
start by sharing how I got introduced to
Locker in one of my previous projects I
had this requirement to set up an
end-to-end application stack including
various different technologies like a
web server using node.js and a database
such as MongoDB and a messaging system
like Redis and an orchestration tool
like ansible we had a lot of issues
developing this application stack with
all these different components first of
all their compatibility with the
underlying OS was an issue we had to
ensure that all these different services
were compatible with the version of OS
we were planning to use there have been
times when certain version of these
services were not compatible with the OS
and we've had to go back and look at
different OS that was compatible with
all of these different services secondly
we had to check the compatibility
between these services and the libraries
and dependencies on the OS we've had
issues where one service requires one
version of a dependent library whereas
another service requires another version
the architecture of our application
changed over time we've had to upgrade
to newer versions of these components or
change the database etc and every time
something changed we had to go through
the same process of checking
compatibility between these various
components and the underlying
infrastructure this compatibility matrix
issue is usually referred to as the
matrix from hell next every time we had
a new developer on board we found it
really difficult to
a new environment the new developers had
to follow a large set of instructions
and run hundreds of commands to finally
set up their environments we had to make
sure they were using the right operating
system the right versions of each of
these components and each developer had
to set all that up by himself each time
we also had different development tests
and production environments one
developer may be comfortable using one
OS and the others may be comfortable
using another one and so we couldn't
guarantee that the application that we
were building would run the same way in
different environments and so all of
this made our life in developing
building and shipping the application
really difficult so I needed something
that could help us with the
compatibility issue and something that
will allow us to modify or change these
components without affecting the other
components and even modify the
underlying operating systems as required
and that search landed me on docker with
docker I was able to run each component
in a separate container with its own
dependencies and its own libraries all
on the same VM and the OS but within
separate environments or containers we
just had to build the docker
configuration once and all our
developers could now get started with a
simple docker run command a respective
of what the underlying operating system
they run all they needed to do was to
make sure they had duck or installed on
their systems so what are containers
containers are completely isolated
environments I think they can have their
own processes for services their own
network interfaces their own mounts just
like washing machines except they all
share the same OS kernel we will look at
what that means in a bit but it's also
important to note that containers are
not new with docker containers have
existed for about 10 years now and some
of the different types of containers are
LX c LX d LX c FS etc docker utilizes
Aleksey containers setting up these
continua environments is hard as they
are very low-level and that is where
docker offers a high-level tool with
several powerful functionalities making
it really easy
for end-users like us to understand how
docker works let us revisit some basic
concepts of operating systems first if
you look at operating systems like
Ubuntu Fedora Susi air scent OS they all
consist of two things an OS kernel and a
set of software the OS kernel is
responsible for interacting with the
underlying hardware while the OS kernel
remains the same which is Linux in this
case it's the software above it that
makes these operating systems different
this software may consist of a different
user interface drivers compilers file
managers developer tools etc so you have
a common Linux kernel shared across all
races and some custom software that
differentiate operating systems from
each other we said earlier that docker
containers share the underlying kernel
so what does that actually mean
sharing the kernel let's say we have a
system with an Ubuntu OS with docker
installed on it docker can run any
flavor of OS on top of it as long as
they are all based on the same kernel in
this case Linux if the underlying OS is
Ubuntu docker can run a container based
on another distribution like debian
fedora SUSE or Sint OS each docker
container only has the additional
software that we just talked about in
the previous slide that makes these
operating systems different and docker
utilizes the underlying kernel of the
docker host which works with all OSS
above so what is an OS that do not share
the same kernel as this Windows and so
you won't be able to run a Windows based
container on a docker host with Linux on
it for that you will require a docker on
a Windows server now it is when I say
this that most of my students go hey
hold on there that's not true and they
install docker on Windows run a
container based on Linux and go see it's
possible well when you install docker on
Windows and run a Linux container on
Windows you're not really running a
Linux container on Windows Windows runs
a Linux container on a Linux virtual
machine under the hood so it's really
Linux
container on Linux virtual machine on
Windows we discuss more about this on
the docker on Windows or Mac later
during this course now you might ask
isn't that a disadvantage then not being
able to run another kernel on the OS the
answer is no because unlike hypervisors
docker is not meant to virtualize and
run different operating systems and
kernels on the same hardware the main
purpose of docker is to package and
container as applications and to ship
them and to run them anywhere any times
as many times as you want so that brings
us to the differences between virtual
machines and containers something that
we tend to do is specially those from a
virtualization background as you can see
on the right in case of docker we have
the underlying hardware infrastructure
and then the OS and then docker
installed on the OS docker then manages
the containers that run with libraries
and dependencies alone in case of
virtual machines we have the hypervisor
like ESX on the hardware and then the
virtual machines on them as you can see
each virtual machine has its own OS
inside it and then the dependencies and
then the application the overhead causes
higher utilization of underlying
resources as there are multiple virtual
operating systems and kernel running the
virtual machines also consume higher
disk space as each VM is heavy and is
usually in gigabytes in size whereas
docker containers are lightweight and
are usually in megabytes in size this
allows docker containers to boot up
faster usually in a matter of seconds
whereas VMs as we know takes minutes to
boot up as it needs to put up the entire
operating system it is also important to
note that docker has less isolation as
more resources are shared between the
containers like kernel
whereas VMs have complete isolation from
each other since VMs don't rely on the
underlying OS or kernel you can run
different types of applications built on
different OSS such as Linux based or
Windows based apps on the same
hypervisor so those are some differences
between the two now having said that
it's not an
either container or virtual machine
situation its containers and virtual
machines now when you have large
environments with thousands of
application containers running on
thousands of dog or hosts you will often
see containers provisioned on virtual
docker hosts that way we can utilize the
advantages of both technologies we can
use the benefits of virtualization to
easily provision or decommission docker
House serves as required at the same
time make use of the benefits of docker
to easily provision applications and
quickly scale them as required but
remember that in this case we will not
be provisioning that many virtual
machines as we used to before because
earlier we provisioned a virtual machine
for each application
now you might provision a virtual
machine for hundreds or thousands of
containers so how is it done there are
lots of containerized versions of
applications readily available as of
today so most organizations have their
products containerized and available in
a public dock or repository called
docker hub or docker store for example
you can find images of most common
operating systems databases and other
services and tools once you identify the
images you need and you install docker
on your hosts bringing up an application
is as easy as running a docker run
command with the name of the image in
this case running a docker run and
single command will run an instance of
ansible
on the docker host similarly run an
instance of MongoDB Redis and nodejs
using the docker run command if we need
to run multiple instances of the web
service simply add as many instances as
you need and configure a load balancer
or some kind in the front in case one of
the instances were to fail
simply destroy that instance and launch
anyone there are other solutions
available for handling such cases that
we will look at later during this course
and for now don't focus too much on the
commands and we will get to that in a
bit we've been talking about images and
containers let's understand the
difference between the two an image is a
package or a template just like a VM
template that you might have worked with
in the virtualization world it is used
to create one or more containers
containers are running instances of
images that are isolated and have their
own environments and set of processors
as we've seen before
a lot of products have been docker iced
already in case you cannot find what
you're looking for you could create your
own image and push it to docker hub
repository making it available for
public so if you look at it
traditionally developers developed
applications then they hand it over to
ops team to deploy and manage it in
production environments they do that by
providing a set of instructions such as
information about how the hosts must be
set up what prerequisites are to be
installed on the host and how the
dependencies are to be configured etc
since the ops team did not really
develop the application on their own
they struggle with setting it up when
the hidden issue they work with the
developers to resolve it with docker the
developers and operations teams work
hand-in-hand to transform the guide into
a docker file with both of their
requirements this docker file is then
used to create an image for their
applications this image can now run on
any host with docker installed on it and
is guaranteed to run the same way
everywhere so the ops team can now
simply use the image to deploy the
application since the image was already
working when the developer built it and
operations are have not modified it it
continues to work the same way when
deployed in production and that's one
example of how a tool like docker
contributes to the DevOps culture well
that's it for now and in the upcoming
lecture we will look at how to get
started with docker we will now see how
to get started with docker
now docker has two editions the
Community Edition and the Enterprise
Edition the Community Edition is the set
of free docker products the Enterprise
Edition is the certified and supported
container platform that comes with
enterprise
add ons like the image management image
security Universal control plane for
managing and orchestrating container
runtimes but of course these come with a
price we will discuss more about
container orchestration later in this
course and along with some alternatives
for now we will go ahead with the
Community Edition the Community Edition
is available on Linux Mac Windows or on
cloud platforms like AWS or Azure in the
upcoming demo we will take a look at how
to install and get started with docker
on a Linux system now if you are on Mac
or Windows you have two options either
install a Linux VM using VirtualBox or
some kind of virtualization platform and
then follow along with the upcoming demo
which is really the most easiest way to
get started with docker the second
option is to install docker Desktop for
Mac or the docker desktop for Windows
which are native applications so if that
is really what you want
check out the docker for Mac and the
Windows sections towards the end of this
course and then head back here once you
are all set up we will now head over to
a demo and we will take a look at how to
install docker on a Linux machine in
this demo we look at how to install and
get started with docker first of all
identify a system physical or virtual
machine or laptop that has a supported
operating system in my case I have an
Ubuntu VM go to doctor comm and click on
get darker you will be taken to the
docker engine Community Edition page
that is the free version that we are
after from the left hand menu select
your system type I choose Linux in my
case and then select your OS flavor
I choose Ubuntu read through the
prerequisites and requirements your abun
to system must be 64-bit and one of
these supported versions like disco
cosmic bio
or Sanyal in my case I have a bionic
version to confirm view the Etsy release
file next uninstall any older version if
one exists so let's just make sure that
there is none on my host so I'll just
copy and paste that command and I
confirm that there are no older version
that exists on my system the next step
is to set up repository and install the
software now there are two ways to go
about this the first is using the
package manager by first updating the
repository using the apt-get update
command then installing the prerequisite
packages and then adding Dockers of
facial GPG keys and then installing
docker but I'm not going to go that
route there is an easier way if you
scroll all the way to the bottom you
will find the instructions to install
docker using the convenience script it's
a script that automates the entire
installation process and works on most
operating systems run the first command
to download a copy of the script and
then run the second command to execute
the script to install docker
automatically give it a few minutes to
complete the installation
the
is now successful that has now checked
the version of docker using the darker
version command we've installed version
19.0 3.1 we will now run a simple
container to ensure everything is
working as expected for this head over
to docker hub at hub docker calm here
you will find a list of the most popular
docker images like engine eggs MongoDB
Alpine nodejs
Redis etc let's search for a fun image
called we'll say we'll say is Dockers
version of cows a which is basically a
simple application that trends a cow
saying something in this case it happens
to be a whale copy the docker run
command given here remember to add a
sudo and we will change the message to
hello world
on running this command docker pulls the
image of the whales II application from
docker hub and runs it and we have our
avail saying hello great we're all set
remember for the purpose of this course
you don't really need to set up a docker
system on your own
we provide hands-on labs that you will
get access to but if you wish to
experiment on your own and follow along
feel free to do so we now look at some
of the docker commands at the end of
this lecture you will go through a
hands-on quiz where you will practice
working with these commands let's start
by looking at docker run command the
docker run command is used to run a
container from an image running the
docker run nginx command will run an
instance of the nginx application on the
docker host if it already exists if the
image is not present on the host it will
go out to docker hub and pull the image
down but this is only done the first
time for the subsequent executions the
same image will be reused the docker PS
command lists all running containers and
some basic information about them such
as the container ID the name of the
image we used to run the containers the
current status and the name of the
container each container automatically
gets a random ID and name created for it
by docker which in this case is silly
Samet to see all containers running or
not use the - a option this outputs all
running as well as previously stopped or
exited containers we will talk about the
command and port fields shown in this
output later in this course for now
let's just focus on the basic commands
to stop a running container use the
Tucker stop command but you must provide
either the container ID or the continue
name in the stop command if you're not
sure of the name run the docker PS
command to get it on success you will
see the name printed out and running
docker PS again will show no running
containers running docker PS - a
however shows the container silly summit
and that it is in an accident states a
few seconds ago now what if we don't
want this container lying around
consuming space what if we want to get
rid of it for good use the docker RM
command to remove a stopped or exited
container permanently if it prints the
name back we're good run the docker PS
command again to verify that it's no
longer present good but what about the
nginx image that was downloaded at first
we're not using that anymore so how do
we get rid of that image but first how
do we see a list of images present on
our hosts run the docker images command
to see a list of available images and
their sizes on our hosts we have four
images the nginx Redis Ubuntu and Alpine
we will talk about tags later in this
course when we discuss about images to
remove an image that you no longer plan
to use run the docker RM I command
remember you must ensure that no
containers are running off of that image
before attempting to remove the image
you must stop and delete all dependent
containers to be able to delete an image
when we ran the docker run command
earlier it downloaded the Ubuntu image
as it couldn't find one locally what if
we simply want to download the image and
keep so when we run the run docker run
command we don't want to wait for it to
download use the docker pull command to
only pull the image and not run the
container so in this case the docker
pull a bull to come and pulls the Ubuntu
image and stores it on our host let's
look at another example say you were to
run a docker container from an Ubuntu
image when you run the docker run Ubuntu
command it runs an instance of a bundle
image and exits immediately if you were
to list the running containers you
wouldn't see the container running if
you list all containers including those
that are stopped you will see that the
new container Iran is in an exited state
now why is that
unlike virtual machines containers are
not meant to host an operating system
containers are meant to run a specific
task or process such as to host an
instance of a web server or application
server or a database or simply to carry
some kind of computation or analysis
tasks once the task is complete the
container exits a container only lives
as long as the process inside it is
alive if the web service inside the
container is stopped or crash then the
container exits this is why when you run
a container from an Ubuntu image it
stops immediately because you bun too is
just an image of an operating system
that is used as the base image for other
applications there is no process or
application running in it by default if
the image isn't running any service as
is the case with Ubuntu you could
instruct docker to run a process with
the docker run command for example a
sleep command with a duration of 5
seconds when the container starts it
runs the sleep command and goes into
sleep for 5 seconds post with the sleep
command exits and the container stops
what we just saw was executing a command
when we run the container but what if we
would like to execute a command on a
running container for example when I run
the docker PS command I can see that
there is a running container which uses
the bun to image and sleeps 400 seconds
so let's say I would like to see the
contents of a file inside this
particular container I could use the
docker exec command to execute a command
on my docker container in this case to
print the contents of the Etsy hosts
file finally let's look at one more
option before we head over to the
practice exercises I'm now going to run
a docker image I developed for a simple
web application the repository name is
called cloud slash simple web app it
runs a simple web server that listens on
port 8080 when you run a docker
c'mon like this it runs in the
foreground or in an attached mode
meaning you will be attached to the
console or the standard out of the
docker container and you will see the
output of the web service on your screen
you won't be able to do anything else on
this console other than view the output
until this docker container stops it
won't respond to your inputs press the
ctrl + C combination to stop the
container and the application hosted on
the container exits and you get back to
your prompt another option is to run the
docker container in the D test mode by
providing the - D option this will run
the docker container in the background
mode and you will be back to your prompt
immediately the container will continue
to run in the back end run the docker PS
command to view the running container
now if you would like to attach back to
the running container later run the
docker attach command and specify the
name or ID of the docker container now
remember if you are specifying the ID of
a container in any docker command you
can simply provide the first few
characters alone just so it is different
from the other container IDs on the host
in this case I specify a 0 for 3 D now
don't worry about accessing the UI of
the webserver for now we will look more
into that in the upcoming lectures for
now let's just understand the basic
commands will now get our hands dirty
with the docker CLI so let's take a look
at how to access the practice lab
environments next
let me now walk you through the hands-on
lab practice environment the links to
access the labs associated with this
course are available at cold cloud at
code cloud comm slash P slash docker
dash labs this link is also given in the
description of this video
once you're on this page use the links
given there to access the labs
associated to your lecture each lecture
has its own lab so remember to choose
the right lab for your lecture
the labs open up right in your browser I
would recommend to use google chrome
while working with the labs the
interface consists of two parts a
terminal on the left and a quiz portal
on the right the cooze portal on the
right gives you challenges to solve
follow the quiz and try and answer the
questions asked and complete the tasks
given to you each scenario consists of
anywhere from 10 to 20 questions that
needs to be answered within 30 minutes
to an hour at the top you have the
question numbers below that is the
remaining time for your lab below that
is the question
if you're not able to solve the
challenge look for hints in the hints
section you may skip a question by
hitting the skip button in the top right
corner but remember that you will not be
able to go back to a previous question
once you have skipped if the quiz portal
gets stuck for some reason click on the
quiz portal tab at the top to open the
quiz portal in a separate window the
terminal gives you access to a real
system running Tucker you can run any
docker command here and run your own
containers or applications you would
typically be running commands to solve
the tasks assigned in the quiz portal
you may play around and experiment with
this environment but make sure you do
that after you've gone through the quiz
so that your work does not interfere
with the tasks provided by the quiz so
let me walk you through a few questions
there are two types of questions each
lab scenario starts with a set of export
multiple-choice questions where you're
asked to explore and find information in
the given environment and select the
right answer this is to get you
familiarized with a set up you are then
asked to perform tasks like run a
container stop them delete them build
your own image etc here the first
question asks us to find the version of
docker server engine running on the host
run the docker reversion command in the
terminal and identify the right version
then select the appropriate option from
the given choices another example is the
fourth question where it asks you to run
a container using the Redis image if
you're not sure of the command click on
hints and it will show you a hint we now
run a Redis container using the docker
run readies command wait for the
container to run once done click on
check to check your work we have now
successfully completed the task
similarly follow along and complete all
tasks once the lab exercise is completed
remember to leave a feedback and let us
know how it went a few things to note
these are publicly accessible labs that
anyone can access so if you catch
yourself logged out during a peak hour
please wait for some time and try again
also remember to not store any private
or confidential data on these systems
remember that this environment is for
learning purposes only and is only alive
for an hour after which the lab is
destroyed so does all your work but you
may start over and access these labs as
many times as you want until you feel
confident I will also post solutions to
these lab quizzes so if you run into
issues you may refer to those that's it
for now header words are the first
challenge and I will see you on the
other side
[Music]
we will now look at some of the other
docker run commands at the end of this
lecture you will go through a hands-on
quiz where you will practice working
with these commands we learned that we
could use the docker run Redis command
to run the container running a Redis
service in this case the latest version
of Redis which happens to be 5.0 to 5 as
of today but what if we want to run
another version of Redis like for
example and older versions say 4.0 then
you specify the version separated by a
colon this is called a tag in that case
docker pulls an image of the 4.0 version
of Redis and runs that also notice that
if you don't specify any tag as in the
first command docker will consider the
default tag to be latest latest is a tag
associated to the latest version of that
software which is governed by the
authors of that software so as a user
how do you find information about these
versions and what is the latest at
docker hub com look up an image and you
will find all the supported tags in its
description each version of the software
can have multiple short and long tags
associated with it as seen here in this
case the version fight of 0.5 also has
the latest tag on it
let's now look at inputs I have a simple
prompt application that when run asks
for my name and on entering my name
prints a welcome message if I were to
docker eyes this application and run it
as a docker container like this it
wouldn't wait for the prompt it just
prints whatever the application is
supposed to print on standard out that
is because by default the docker
container does not listen to a standard
input even though you are attached to
its console it is not able to read any
input from you it doesn't have a
terminal to read in
what's from it runs in a non-interactive
mud if you would like to provide your
input
you must map the standard input of your
host to the docker container using the -
I parameter the - I parameter is for
interactive mode and when I input my
name it prints the expected output but
there is something still missing from
this the prompt when we run the app at
first it asked us for our name but when
docker iced that prompt is missing
even though it seems to have accepted my
input that is because the application
prompt on the terminal and we have not
attached to the containers terminal for
this use the - T option as well the - T
stands for a sudo terminal so with the
combination of - int we are now attached
to the terminal as well as in an
interactive mode on the container we
will now look at port mapping or port
publishing on containers let's go back
to the example where we run a simple web
application in a docker container on my
docker host remember the underlying host
where docker is installed is called
docker host or docker engine when we run
a containerized web application it runs
and we are able to see that the server
is running but how does a user access my
application as you can see my
application is listening on port 5,000
so I could access my application by
using port 5000 but what IP do I use to
access it from a web browser there are
two options available one is to use the
IP of the docker container every docker
container gets an IP assigned by default
in this case it is 172 dot 17.0 - but
remember that this is an internal IP and
is only accessible within the docker
host so if you open a browser from
within the docker host you can go to
http colon forward slash forward slash
172 dot 17 dot 0 dot 1
: 5,000 to access the IP address but
since this is an internal IP users
outside of the docker host cannot access
it using this IP for this we could use
the IP of the docker host which is one
ninety two dot one sixty eight dot 1.5
but for that to work you must have
mapped the port inside the docker
container to a free port on the docker
host for example if I want the users to
access my application through port 80 on
my docker host I could map port 80 of
local host to port 5000 on the docker
container using the dash P parameter in
my run command like this and so the user
can access my application by going to
the URL HTTP colon slash slash one
ninety two dot one sixty eight dot one
dot five colon 80 and all traffic on
port 80 on my daugher host will get
routed to port 5000 inside the docker
container this way you can run multiple
instances of your application and map
them to different ports on the docker
host or run instances of different
applications on different ports for
example in this case and running an
instance of MySQL that runs a database
on my host and listens on the default
MySQL port which happens to be three
3:06
or another instance of MySQL on another
port eight 3:06 so you can run as many
applications like this and map them to
as many ports as you want and of course
you cannot map to the same port on the
docker host more than once we will
discuss more about port mapping and
networking of containers in the network
lecture later on let's now look at how
data is persisted in a docker container
for example let's say you were to run a
MySQL container when databases and
tables are created the data files are
stored in location /wor Labe MySQL
inside the docker container remember
the docker container has its own
isolated filesystem and any changes to
any files happen within the container
let's assume you dump a lot of data into
the database what happens if you were to
delete the MySQL container and remove it
as soon as you do that the container
along with all the data inside it gets
blown away
meaning all your data is gone if you
would like to persist data you would
want to map a directory outside the
container on the docker host to a
directory inside the container in this
case I create a directory called /opt
slash data dir and map that to var Lib
MySQL inside the docker container using
the - V option and specifying the
directory on the docker host followed by
a colon and the directory inside the
gawker container
this way when docker container runs it
will implicitly mount the external
directory to a folder inside the docker
container this way all your data will
now be stored in the external volume at
/opt slash data directory and thus will
remain even if you delete the docker
container the docker PS command is good
enough to get basic details about
containers like their names and ID's but
if you would like to see additional
details about a specific container use
the docker
inspect command and provide the
container name or ID it returns all
details of a container in a taste on
format such as the state Mounds
configuration data network settings etc
remember to use it when you're required
to find details on a container and
finally how do we see the logs of a
container we ran in the background for
example I ran my simple web application
using the - D parameter and it ran the
container in a detached mode how do I
view the logs which happens to be the
contents written to the standard out of
that container use the docker logs
command and specify the container ID or
name like this
well a sit for this lecture head over to
the challenges and practice working with
docker commands so to start with a
simple web application written in Python
this piece of code is used to create a
web application that displays a web page
with a background color if you look
closely into the application code you
will see a line that sets the background
color to red now that works just fine
however if you decide to change the
color in the future you will have to
change the application code it is a best
practice to move such information out of
the application code and into say an
environment variable called app color
the next time you run the application
set an environment variable called app
color to a desired value and the
application now has a new color once
your application gets packaged into a
docker image he would then run it with
the docker run command followed by the
name of the image however if you wish to
pass the environment variable as we did
before he would now use the docker run
commands - II option to set an
environment variable within the
container to deploy multiple containers
with different colors he would run the
docker command multiple times and set a
different value for the environment
variable each time so how do you find
the environment variable set on a
container that's already running use the
docker inspect command to inspect the
properties of a running container under
the config section you will find the
list of environment variables set on the
container well that's it for this
lecture on configuring environment
variables in docker
[Music]
hello and welcome to this lecture on
docker images in this lecture we're
going to see how to create your own
image now before that why would you need
to create your own image it could either
be because you cannot find a component
or a service that you want to use as
part of your application on docker hub
already or you and your team decided
that the application you're developing
will be derived for ease of shipping and
deployment in this case I'm going to
containerize an application a simple web
application that I have built using the
Python flask framework first we need to
understand what we our container izing
or what application we are creating an
image for and how the application is
built so start by thinking what you
might do if you want to deploy the
application manually we write down the
steps required in the right order and
creating an image for a simple web
application if I were to set it up
manually I would start with an operating
system like Ubuntu then update the
source repositories using the apt
command then install dependencies using
the apt command then install Python
dependencies using the PIP command then
copy over the source code of my
application to a location like opt and
then finally run the web server using
the flask command now that I have the
instructions create a docker file using
this here's a quick overview of the
process of creating your own image first
create a docker file named docker file
and write down the instructions for
setting up your application in it such
as installing dependencies where to copy
the source code from and to and what the
entry point of the application is etc
once done build your image using the
docker build command and specify the
docker file as input as well as a tag
name
for the image this will create an image
locally on your system to make it
available on the public docker hub
registry run the docker push command and
specify the name of the image you just
created in this case the name of the
image is my account name which is M
Amjad followed by the image name which
is my custom app now let's take a closer
look at that docker file docker file is
a text file written in a specific format
that docker can understand it's in an
instruction and arguments format for
example in this docker file everything
on the left in caps is an instruction in
this case from run copy and entry point
are all instructions each of these
instruct docker to perform a specific
action while creating the image
everything on the right is an argument
to those instructions the first line
from Ubuntu defines what the base OS
should be for this container every
docker image must be based off of
another image either an OS or another
image that was created before based on
an OS you can find official releases of
all operating systems on docker hub it's
important to note that all docker files
must start with a from instruction the
run instruction instructs docker to run
a particular command on those base
images so at this point docker runs the
apt-get update commands to fetch the
updated packages and installs required
dependencies on the image then the copy
instruction copies files from the local
system onto the docker image in this
case the source code of our application
is in the current folder and I will be
copying it over to the location opt
source code inside the docker image and
finally entry point allows us to specify
a command that will be run when the
image is run as a container
when docker builds the images it builds
these in a layered architecture each
line of instruction creates a new layer
in the docker image with just the
changes from the previous layer for
example the first layer is a base Ubuntu
OS followed by the second instruction
that creates a second layer which
installs all the apt packages and then
the third instruction creates a third
layer with the Python packages followed
by the fourth layer that copies the
source code over and the final layer
that updates the entry point of the
image since each layer only stores the
changes from the previous layer it is
reflected in the size as well if you
look at the base opened to image it is
around 120 MB in size the apt packages
that I install is around 300 MB and the
remaining layers are small you could see
this information if you run the docker
history command followed by the image
name when you run the door
Bilka man you could see the various
steps involved and the result of each
task all the layers built are cast
so the layered architecture helps you
restart docker built from that
particular step in case it fails or if
you were to add new steps in the build
process you wouldn't have to start all
over again all the layers built are
cached by docker so in case a particular
step was to fail for example in this
case step three failed and you were to
fix the issue and rerun docker build it
will reuse the previous layers from
cache and continue to build the
remaining layers the same is true if you
were to add additional steps in the
docker file this way rebuilding your
image is faster and you don't have to
wait for docker to rebuild the entire
image each time this is helpful
especially when you update source code
of your application as it may change
more frequently only the layers above
the updated layers needs to be rebuilt
we just saw a number of products
containerized such as databases
development tools operating systems etc
but that's just not it you can
containerized almost all of the
application even simple ones like
browsers or utilities like curl
applications like Spotify Skype etc
basically you can containerize
everything and going forward and see
that's how everyone is going to run
applications nobody is going to install
anything anymore going forward instead
they're just going to run it using
docker and when they don't need it
anymore
get rid of it easily without having to
clean up too much
[Music]
in this lecture we will look at commands
arguments and entry points in docker
let's start with a simple scenario say
you were to run a docker container from
an Ubuntu image when you run the docker
run Ubuntu command it runs an instance
of Ubuntu image and exits immediately if
you were to list the running containers
you wouldn't see the container running
if you list all containers including
those that are stopped you will see that
the new container
you ran is in an excited state now why
is that unlike virtual machines
containers are not meant to host an
operating system containers are meant to
run a specific task or process such as
to host an instance of a web server or
application server or a database or
simply to carry out some kind of
computation or analysis once the task is
complete
the container exits a container only
lives as long as the process inside it
is alive if the web service inside the
container is dot or crashes the
container exits so who defines what
process is run within the container if
you look at the docker file for popular
docker images like ng INX
you will see an instruction called CMD
which stands for command that defines
the program that will be run within the
container when it starts for the ng INX
image it is the ng INX command for the
MySQL image it is the MySQL D command
what we tried to do earlier was to run a
container with a plain Ubuntu operating
system let us look at the docker file
for this image you will see that it uses
bash as the default command now bash is
not really a process like a web server
or database server it is a shell that
listens for inputs from a terminal if it
cannot find the terminal it exits when
we ran the ubuntu container earlier
docker created a container from the
ubuntu image
launched the bash program by default
docker does not attach a terminal to a
container when it is run and so the bash
program does not find the terminal and
so it exits since the process that was
started when the container was created
finished the container exits as well so
how do you specify a different command
to start the container one option is to
append a command to the docker run
command and that way it overrides the
default command specified with him the
image in this case I run the docker run
Ubuntu command with the sleep 5 command
as the added option this way when the
container starts it runs the sleep
program waits for 5 seconds and then
exits but how do you make that change
permanent say you want the image to
always run the sleep command when it
starts you would then create your own
image from the base ubuntu image and
specify a new command there are
different ways of specifying the command
either the command simply as is in a
shell form or in a JSON array format
like this but remember when you specify
in a JSON array format the first element
in the array should be the executable in
this case the sleep program do not
specify the command and parameters
together like this the command and its
parameters should be separate elements
in the list so I now build my new image
using the docker build command and name
it as Ubuntu sleeper I could now simply
run the docker ubuntu sleeper command
and get the same results it always
sleeps for 5 seconds and exits but what
if I wished to change the number of
seconds it sleeps currently it is
hard-coded
to 5 seconds as we learned before one
option is to run the docker run command
with the new command appended to it in
this case sleep 10 and so the command
that will be run at startup will be
sleep 10
but it doesn't look very good the name
of the image
ubuntu sleeper in itself implies that
the container will sleep so we shouldn't
have to specify the sleep command again
instead we would like it to be something
like this docker run ubuntu sleeper 10
we only want to pass in the number of
seconds the container should sleep and
sleep command should be invoked
automatically and that is where the
entry point instructions comes into play
the entry point instruction is like the
command instruction as in you can
specify the program that will be run
when the container starts and whatever
you specify on the command line in this
case 10 will get appended to the entry
point so the command that will be run
when the container starts is sleep 10 so
that's the difference between the two in
case of the CMD instruction the command
line parameters passed will get replaced
entirely whereas in case of entry point
the command line parameters will get
appended now in the second case what if
I run the ubuntu sleeper image command
without appending the number of seconds
then the command at startup will be just
sleep and you get the error that the
operand is missing so how do you
configure a default value for the
command if one was not specified in the
command line that's where you would use
both entry point as well as the command
instruction in this case the command
instruction will be appended to the
entry point instruction so at startup
the command would be sleep 5 if you
didn't specify any parameters in the
command line if you did then that will
override the command instruction and
remember for this to happen you should
always specify the entry point and
command instructions in it JSON format
finally what if you really really want
to modify the entry point during runtime
say from sleep to an imaginary sleep 2.0
command well in that case you can
override
by using the entry point option in the
docker run command the final command a
startup would then be sleep 2.0 10 well
that's it for this lecture and I will
see you in the next we now look at
networking in docker when you install
docker it creates three networks
automatically bridge no and host bridge
is the default Network a container gets
attached to if you would like to
associate the container with any other
network is specified the network
information using the network command
line parameter like this we will now
look at each of these networks the BRIT
network is a private internal network
created by docker on the host all
containers attached to this network by
default and they get an internal IP
address usually in the range 170 2.17
series the containers can access each
other using this internal IP if required
to access any of these containers from
the outside world map the ports of these
containers to ports on the docker host
as we have seen before another way to
access the containers externally is to
associate the container to the hosts
network this takes out any network
isolation between the docker host and
the docker container meaning if you were
to run a web server on port 5000 in a
web app container it is automatically as
accessible on the same port externally
without requiring any port mapping as
the web container uses the hosts network
this would also mean that unlike before
you will now not be able to run multiple
web containers on the same host on the
same port as the ports are now common to
all containers in the host
network with the non network the
container
are not attached to any network and
doesn't have any access to the external
network or other containers they run in
an isolated Network so we just saw the
default burst network with the network
ID 170 2.72 0.1 so all containers
associated to this default network will
be able to communicate to each other but
what if we wish to isolate the
containers within the docker host for
example the first two web containers on
internal network 172 and the second two
containers on a different internal
network like 182 by default docker only
creates one internal bridge network we
could create our own internal network
using the command docker Network create
and specified the driver which is bridge
in this case and the subnet for that
network followed by the custom isolated
network name run the docker network LS
command to list all networks so how do
we see the network settings and the IP
address assigned to an existing
container run the docker inspect command
with the ID or name of the container and
you will find a section on network
settings there you can see the type of
network the container is attached to is
internal IP address MAC address and
other settings containers can reach each
other using their names for example in
this case I have a webserver and a MySQL
database container running on the same
node how can I get my web server to
access the database on the database
container one thing I could do is to use
the internal IP address signed to the
MySQL container which in this case is
170 2.72 0.3 but that is not very ideal
because it is not guaranteed that the
container will get the same IP when the
system reboots the right way to do it is
to use the container name all containers
in a docker host can resolve each
other.we
the name of the container docker has a
built-in DNS server that helps the
containers to resolve each other using
the container name
note that the built in DNS server always
runs at address 127 dot 0 dot 0 dot 11
so how does docker implement networking
what's the technology behind it like how
are the containers isolated within the
host docker uses network namespaces that
creates a separate name space for each
container it then uses virtual Ethernet
pairs to connect containers together
well that's all we can talk about it for
now
more about these are advanced concepts
that we discussed in the advanced course
on docker on code cloud that's all for
now from this lecture on networking head
over to the practice tests and practice
working with networking in docker I will
see you in the next lecture hello and
welcome to this lecture and we are
learning advanced docker concepts in
this lecture we're going to talk about
docker storage drivers and file systems
we're going to see where and how docker
stores data and how it manages file
systems of the containers let us start
with how docker stores data on the local
file system
when you install docker on a system it
creates this folder structure at where
lib docker you have multiple folders
under it called a ufs containers image
volumes etc this is where docker stores
all its data by default when I say data
I mean files related to images and
containers running on the docker host
for example all files related to
containers are stored under the
containers folder and the files related
to images are stored under the image
folder any volumes created by the docker
containers are created under the volumes
folder
well don't worry about that for now we
will come back to that in a bit for now
let's just understand where docker
stores its files and in what format so
how exactly does docker store the files
of an image and a container to
understand that we need to understand
Dockers layered architecture let's
quickly recap something we learned when
docker builds images it builds these in
a layered architecture each line of
instruction in the docker file creates a
new layer in the docker image with just
the changes from the previous layer for
example the first layer is a base Ubuntu
operating system followed by the second
instruction that creates a second layer
which installs all the apt packages and
then the third instruction creates a
third layer which with the Python
packages followed by the fourth layer
that copies the source code over and
then finally the fifth layer that
updates the entry point of the image
since each layer only stores the changes
from the previous layer it is reflected
in the size as well if you look at the
base open to image it is around 120
megabytes in size the apt packages that
I install is around 300 MB and then the
remaining layers are small to understand
the advantages of this layered
architecture let's consider a second
application this application has a
different talker file but it's very
similar to our first application as in
it uses the same base image as Ubuntu
uses the same Python and flask
dependencies but uses a different source
code to create a different application
and so a different entry point as well
when I run the docker build command to
build a new image for this application
since the first three layers of both the
applications are the same docker
is not going to build the first three
layers instead it reuses the same three
layers it built for the first
application from the cache and only
creates the last two layers with the new
sources and the new entry point this way
docker builds images faster and
efficiently saves disk space this is
also applicable if you were to update
your application code whenever you
update your application code such as the
app dot py in this case
docker simply reuses all the previous
layers from cache and quickly rebuilds
the application image by updating the
latest source code thus saving us a lot
of time hearing rebuilds and updates
let's rearrange the layers bottom up so
we can understand it better at the
bottom we have the base open to layer
than the packages then the dependencies
and then the source code of the
application and then the entry point all
of these layers are created when we run
the docker build command to form the
final docker image so all of these are
the docker image layers once the build
is complete you cannot modify the
contents of these layers and so they are
read-only and you can only modify them
by initiating a new build when you run a
container based off of this image using
the docker run command docker creates a
container based off of these layers and
creates a new writable layer on top of
the image layer the writable layer is
used to store data created by the
container such as log files written by
the applications any temporary files
generated by the container or just any
file modified by the user on that
container the life of this layer though
is only as long as the container is
alive when the container is destroyed
this layer and all of the changes stored
in it are also destroyed remember that
the same image layer is shared by all
containers created using this image if I
were to log in to the newly created
container and say create
a new file called temp dot txt it will
create that file in the container layer
which is read and write we just said
that the files in the image layer are
read-only meaning you cannot edit
anything in those layers let's take an
example of our application code since we
bake our code into the image the code is
part of the image layer and as such is
read-only after running a container what
if I wish to modify the source code to
say test a change remember the same
image layer may be shared between
multiple containers created from this
image so does it mean that I cannot
modify this file inside the container no
I can still modify this file but before
I save the modified file docker
automatically creates a copy of the file
in the readwrite layer and I will then
be modifying a different version of the
file in the readwrite layer all future
modifications will be done on this copy
of the file in the readwrite layer this
is called copy-on-write mechanism the
image layer being read-only just means
that the files in these layers will not
be modified in the image itself so the
image will remain the same all the time
until you rebuild the image using the
docker build command what happens when
we get rid of the container all of the
data that was stored in the container
layer also gets deleted the change we
made to the app dot py and the new temp
file we created we'll also get removed
so what if we wish to persist this data
for example if we were working with our
database and we would like to preserve
the data created by the container we
could add a persistent volume to the
container to do this first create a
volume using the docker volume create
command so when I run the docker volume
create data underscore volume command it
creates a folder called data underscore
volume under the var Lib docker
volumes directory then when I run the
docker container using the docker run
command I could mount this volume inside
the docker containers read/write layer
using the - B option like this so I
would do a docker run - V then specify
my newly created volume name followed by
a colon and the location inside my
container which is the default location
where MySQL stores data and that is
where Lib MySQL and then the image name
MySQL this will create a new container
and mount the data volume we created
into very Lib MySQL folder inside the
container so all data are written by the
database is in fact stored on the volume
created on the docker host even if the
container is destroyed the data is still
active now what if you didn't run the
docker volume create command to create
the volume before the docker run command
for example if I run the docker run
command to create a new instance of
MySQL container with the volume data
underscore volume to which I have not
created yet docker will automatically
create a volume named data underscore
volume - and mounted to the container
you should be able to see all these
volumes if you list the contents of the
where Lib docker volumes folder this is
called volume mounting as we are
mounting a volume created by docker
under the var Lib docker volumes folder
but what if we had our data already at
another location for example let's say
we have some external storage on the
docker host at four slash data and we
would like to store database data on
that volume and not in the default where
Lib docker volumes folder in that case
we would run a container using the
command docker run - V but in this case
we will provide the complete path to the
folder we would like to mount that is
for slash data for slash minus QL
so it will create a container and mount
the folder to the container this is
called bind mounting so there are two
types of mounts a volume mounting and a
bind mount volume mount mounts a volume
from the volumes directory and bind
mount mounts a directory from any
location on the docker host
one final point note before I let you go
you think the - V is an old style the
new way is to use - mount option the - -
mount is the preferred way as it is more
verbose so you have to specify each
parameter in a key equals value format
for example the previous command can be
written with the - mount option as this
using the type source and target options
the type in this case is bind the source
is the location on my host and target is
the location on my container so who is
responsible for doing all of these
operations maintaining the layered
architecture creating a writable layer
moving files across layers to enable
copy and write etc it's the storage
drivers so Dockery uses storage drivers
to enable layered architecture some of
the common storage drivers are au FS
btrfs ZFS device mapper overlay and
overlay to the selection of the storage
driver depends on the underlying OS
being used for example we to bond to the
default storage driver is a u FS whereas
this storage driver is not available on
other operating systems like fedora or
cent OS in that case device mapper may
be a better option docker will choose
the best storage driver available
automatically based on the operating
system the different storage drivers
also provide different performance and
stability characteristics so you may
want to choose one that fits the needs
of your application and your
organization if you would like to read
more on any of these storage drivers
please refer to the links in the
attached documentation for now that is
all from the docker architecture
concepts see you in the next lecture
[Music]
hello and welcome to this lecture on
docker compose going forward we will be
working with configurations in yamo file
so it is important that you are
comfortable with llamo let's recap a few
things real quick course we first
learned how to run a docker container
using the docker run command if we
needed to set up a complex application
running multiple services a better way
to do it is to use docker compose with
docker compose we could create a
configuration file in yamo format called
docker compose Gemmell and put together
the different services and the options
specific to this to running them in this
file then we could simply run a docker
compose up command to bring up the
entire application stack this is easier
to implement run and maintain as all
changes are always stored in the docker
compose configuration file however this
is all only applicable to running
containers on a single docker host and
for now don't worry about the yamo file
we will take a closer look at the yamo
file in a bit and see how to put it
together that was a really simple
application that I put together let us
look at a better example I'm going to
use the same sample application that
everyone uses to demonstrate docker it's
a simple yet comprehensive application
developed by docker to demonstrate the
various features available in running an
application stack on docker
so let's first get familiarized with the
application because we will be working
with the same application in different
sections through the rest of this course
this is a sample voting application
which provides an interface for a user
to vote and another interface to show
the results the application consists of
various components such as
the voting app which is a web
application developed in Python to
provide the user with an interface to
choose between two options a cat and a
dog when you make a selection the vote
is stored in Redis for those of you who
are new to Redis Redis in this case
serves as a database in memory this load
is then processed by the worker which is
an application written in dotnet the
worker application takes the new vote
and updates the persistent database
which is a Postgres SQL in our case the
Postgres SQL simply has a table with the
number of votes for each category cats
and dogs in this case it increments the
number of votes for cats as our what was
for cats finally the result of the vote
is displayed in a web interface which is
another web application developed in
node.js this resulting application reads
the count of votes from the Postgres
sequel database and displays it to the
user so that is the architecture and
data flow of this simple voting
application stack as you can see this
sample application is built with a
combination of different services
different development tools and multiple
different development platforms such as
Python node.js net etc this sample
application will be used to showcase how
easy it is to set up an entire
application stack consisting of diverse
components in docker let us keep aside
docker swarm services and stacks for a
minute and see how we can put together
this application stack on a single
docker engine using first docker run
commands and then docker compose let us
assume that all images of applications
are already built and are available on
docker repository let us start with the
data layer first we run the docker run
command to start an instance of Redis by
running the docker run Redis command
we will add the dash D parameter to run
this container in the background and we
will also name the container Redis now
naming the containers is important why
is that important
hold that thought we will come to that
in a bit next we will deploy the
Postgres sequel database by running the
docker run Postgres command this time -
we will add the - d option to run this
in the background and name this
container DB for database next we will
start with the application services we
will deploy a front-end app for voting
interface by running an instance of
voting app image run the docker run
command and name the instance vote since
this is a web server it has a web UI
instance running on port 80 we will
publish that port to 5000 on the host
system so we can access it from a
browser next we will deploy the result
web application that shows the results
to the user for this we deploy a
container using the results - app image
and publish port 80 - port 5001 on the
host this way we can access the web UI
of the resulting app on a browser
finally we deploy the worker by running
an instance of the worker image okay now
this is all good and we can see that all
the instances are running on the host
but there is some problem it just does
not seem to work the problem is that we
have successfully run all the different
containers but we haven't actually
linked them together as in we haven't
told the voting web application to use
this particular Redis instance there
could be multiple Redis instances
running we haven't told the worker and
the resulting app to use this particular
Postgres equal database that we ran so
how do we do that that is where we use
links link is a command line option
which can be used to link two containers
together for example the voltage
app web service is dependent on the
Redis service when the web server starts
as you can see in this piece of code on
the web server it looks for a Redis
service running on host Redis but the
voting app container cannot resolve a
host by the name Redis to make the
voting app aware of the Redis service we
add a link option while running the
voting app container to link it to the
Redis container adding a - - link option
to the docker run command and specifying
the name of the Redis container which is
which in this case is Redis followed by
a colon and the name of the host that
the voting app is looking for which is
also Redis in this case remember that
this is why we named the container when
we ran it the first time so we could use
its name while creating a link what this
is in fact doing is it creates an entry
into the e.t.c host file on the voting
app container adding an entry with a
host name Redis with an internal IP of
the Redis container
similarly we add a link for the result
app to communicate with the database by
adding a link option to refer the
database by the name DB as you can see
in this source code of the application
it makes an attempt to connect to a
Postgres database on hosts DB finally
the worker application requires access
to both the Redis as well as the
Postgres database so we add two links to
the worker application one link to link
the Redis and the other link to link
Postgres database note that using links
this way is deprecated and the support
may be removed in future in docker this
is because as we will see in some time
advanced and newer concepts in docker
swarm and networking supports better
ways of achieving what we just did here
with links but I wanted to mention that
anyway so you learned the concept from
the very basics once we have the
run commands tested and ready it is easy
to generate a docker compose file from
it we start by creating a dictionary of
container names we will use the same
name we used in the docker run commands
so we take all the names and create a
key with each of them
then under each item we specify which
image to use the key is the image and
the value is the name of the image to
use next inspect the commands and see
what are the other options used we
published ports so let's move those
ports under the respective containers so
we create a property called ports and
lists all the ports that you would like
to publish under that finally we are
left with links so whichever container
requires a link created properly under
it called links and provide an array of
links such as Redis or TB note that you
could also specify the name of the link
this way without the semicolon and and
the target target name and it will
create a link with the same name as the
target name specifying the DB : DB is
similar to simply specify dB we will
assume the same value to create a link
now that we are all done with our docker
compose file bringing up the stack is
really simple from the docker compose up
command to bring up the entire
application stack when we looked
example of the sample voting application
we assumed that all images are already
built out of the five different
components two of them Redis and
Postgres images we know are already
available on docker hub there are
official images from Redis and Postgres
but the remaining three are our own
application it is not necessary that
they are already built and available in
a docker registry if we would like to
instruct docker compose to run a docker
build instead of trying to pull an image
we can replace the image line with a
build line and specify the location of a
directory which contains the application
code and a docker file with instructions
to build the docker image in this
example for the voting app have all the
application code in a folder named vote
which contains all application code and
a docker file this time when you run the
docker compose up command it will first
build the images give a temporary name
for it and then use those images to run
containers using the options you
specified before similarly use build
option to build the two other services
from the respective folders we will now
look at different versions of docker
compose file this is important because
you might see docker compose files in
different formats at different places
and wonder white-sand look different
docker compose evolved over time and now
supports a lot more options than it did
in the beginning for example this is the
trimmed down version of the docker
compose file we used earlier this is in
fact the original version of docker
compose file known as version 1 this had
a number of limitations for example if
you wanted to deploy containers on a
different network other than the default
bridge network there was no way of
specifying that in this version of the
file also say you have a dependency
or startup order of some kind for
example your database container must
come up first and only then and should
the voting application be started there
was no way you could specify that in the
ocean one of the docker compose file
support for these came in version 2 with
version 2 and up the format of the file
also changed a little bit you no longer
specify your stack information directly
as you did before it is all encapsulated
in a Services section so create a
property called services in the root of
the file and then move all the services
underneath that you will still use the
same docker compose up command to bring
up your application stack but how does
docker compose know what version of the
file you're using you're free to use
version 1 or version 2 depending on your
needs so how does the docker compose
know what format you are using for
version 2 and up you must specify the
version of docker compose file you are
intending to use by specifying the
version at the top of the file in this
case version : 2 another difference is
with networking in version 1 docker
compose attaches all the containers it
runs to the default bridged Network and
then use links to enable communication
between the containers as we did before
with version 2 dr. Campos automatically
creates a dedicated bridged Network for
this application and then attaches all
containers to that new network all
containers are then able to communicate
to each other using each other's service
name
so you basically don't need to use links
in version 2 of docker compose you can
simply get rid of all the links you
mentioned in version 1 when you convert
a file from version one to version two
and finally version 2 also introduces it
depends on feature if you wish to
specify a startup
order for instance say the watering web
application is dependent on the Redis
service so you need to ensure that Redis
container is started first and only then
the voting web application must be
started we could add a depends on
property to the voting application and
indicate that it is dependent on Redis
then comes version 3 which is the latest
as of today version 3 is similar to
version 2 in the structure meaning it
has a version specification at the top
and a Services section under which you
put all your services just like in
version 2 make sure to specify the
version number as 3 at the top version 3
comes with support for docker swamp
which we will see later on there are
some options that were removed and added
to see details on those you can refer to
the documentation section using the link
in the reference page following this
lecture we will see version 3 in much
detail later when we discuss about
docker stacks let us talk about networks
in docker compose getting back to our
application so far we have been just
deploying all containers on the default
bridged Network let us say we modify the
architecture a little bit to contain the
traffic from the different sources for
example we would like to separate the
user generated traffic from the
applications internal traffic so we
create a front-end network dedicated for
traffic from users and a back-end
network dedicated for traffic within the
application we then connect the user
facing applications which are the voting
app and the result app to the front-end
network and all the components to an
internal back-end network so
back in our docker compose file note
that I have actually stripped out the
port section for simplicity sake they're
still there but they're just not shown
here the first thing we need to do if we
were to use networks is to define the
networks we are going to use in our case
we have two networks front end and back
end so create a new property called
networks at the root level adjacent to
the services in the docker compose file
and add a map of networks we are
planning to use then under each service
create a network's property and provide
a list of networks that service must be
attached to in case of Redis and DB it's
only the back-end network in case of the
front-end applications such as a
devoting app and the result app they
require to be attached to both a
front-end and back-end Network you must
also add a section for worker container
to be added to the back-end network I
have just omitted that in this slide due
to space constraints now that you have
seen docker compose files head over to
the coding exercises and practice
developing some docker compose files
that's it for this lecture and I will
see you in the next lecture
[Music]
we will now look at docker registry so
what is a registry if the containers
were the rain then they would rain from
the docker registry which are the clouds
that's where docker images are stored
it's a central repository of all docker
images let's look at a simple nginx
container we run the docker run engine X
command to run an instance of the nginx
image let's take a closer look at that
image name now the name is nginx
but what is this image and where is this
image pulled from this name follows
Dockers image naming convention nginx
here is the image or the repository name
when you say nginx
it's actually nginx slash nginx the
first part stands for the user or
account name
so if you don't provide an account or a
repository name it assumes that it is
the same as the given name which in this
case is nginx the user names is usually
your docker hub account name or if it is
an organization then it's the name of
the organization if you were to create
your own account and create your own
repositories or images under it then you
would use a similar pattern now where
are these images stored and pulled from
since we have not specified the location
where these images are to be pulled from
it is assumed to be on Dockers default
registry docker hub the dns name for
which is darker dial the registry is
where all the images are stored whenever
you create a new image or update an
existing image you push it to the
registry and every time anyone deploys
this application it is pulled from that
registry there are many other popular
registries as well for example Google's
registry is at GCR that I offer a lot of
kubernetes related images are stored
like the ones used for performing
end-to-end tests on the cluster these
are all publicly accessible in
just that anyone can download and access
when you have applications built
in-house that shouldn't be made
available to the public hosting an
internal private registry may be a good
solution many cloud service providers
such as AWS as your GCP provide a
private registry by default when you
open an account with them on any of
these solutions be a docker hub or
Google registry or your internal private
registry you may choose to make a
repository private so that it can only
be accessed using a set of credentials
from Dockers perspective to run a
container using an image from a private
registry you first log in to your
private registry using the docker login
command input your credentials once
successful run the application using
private registry as part of the image
name like this now if you did not log
into the private registry it will come
back saying that the image cannot be
found so remember to always log in
before pulling or pushing to a private
registry we said that cloud providers
like AWS or GCP provide a private
registry when you create an account with
them but what if you are running your
application on-premise and don't have a
private registry how do you deploy your
own private registry within your
organization the docker registry is
itself another application and of course
is available as a docker image the name
of the image is registry and it exposes
the API on port 5,000 now that you have
your custom registry running at port
5,000 on this docker host how do you
push your own image to it use the docker
image tag command to tag the image with
a private registry URL in it in this
case since it's running on the same door
host I can use localhost
semi colon 5,000 followed by the image
name I can then push my image to my
local private registry using the command
docker push and the new image name with
the docker registry information in it
from there on I can pull my image from
anywhere
within this network using either
localhost if you're on the same host or
the IP or domain name of my docker host
if I'm accessing from another host in my
environment well let's sit for this
lecture
hello words of the practice test and
practice working with private docker
registries welcome to this lecture on
docker engine in this lecture we will
take a deeper look at Dockers
architecture how it actually runs
applications in isolated containers and
how it works under the hood docker
engine as we have learned before is
simply referred to a host with docker
installed on it when you install docker
on a Linux host you're actually
installing three different components
the docker daemon the rest api server
and the docker CLI the docker daemon is
a background process that manages docker
objects such as the images containers
volumes and networks the docker rest api
server is the api interface that
programs can use to talk to the daemon
and provide instructions you could
create your own tools using this REST
API and the docker CLI is nothing but
the command-line interface that we've
been using until now to perform actions
such as running a container stopping
containers destroying images etc it uses
the REST API to interact with the docker
demon something to note here is that the
docker CLI need not necessarily be on
the same host it could be on another
system like a laptop and can still work
with a remote docker engine simply use
the dash H option on the docker command
and specify the remote docker engine
address and a port as shown here for
example to run a container based on ng I
and X on a remote docker host run the
command docker dash H equals 10.1 23
2000 call n' to 375 run ngan
now let's try and understand how exactly
our applications containerized in docker
how does it work
under the hood docker uses namespaces to
isolate workspace process IDs network
inter-process communication mounds and
unix time sharing systems are created in
their own namespace thereby providing
isolation between containers let's take
a look at one of the namespace isolation
technique process ID namespaces whenever
a Linux system boots up it starts with
just one process with a process ID of
one this is the root process and kicks
off all the other processes in the
system by the time the system boots up
completely we have a handful of
processors running this can be seen by
running the PS command to list all the
running processes the process IDs are
unique and two processes cannot have the
same process ID now if we were to create
a container which is basically like a
child system within the current system
the child system needs to think that it
is an independent system on its own and
it has its own set of processes
originating from a root process with a
process ID of one but we know that there
is no hard isolation between the
containers and the underlying host so
the processes running inside the
container or in fact processes running
on the underlying host and so two
processes cannot have the same process
ID of one this is where namespaces come
in to play with process ID namespaces
each process can have multiple process
IDs associated with it for example when
the processes start in the container
it's actually just another set of
processes on the base Linux system and
it gets the next available process ID in
this case 5 & 6 however they also get
another process ID starting with PID 1
in the container name space which is
only visible inside the container so the
container things that it has its own
route process tree and so it is an
independent system so how does that
relate to an actual system how do you
see this on a host let's say I were to
run an ng I in X Server as a container
we know that the nginx container
runs an NGO next service if we were to
list all the services inside the docker
container we see that the ng ionic
service running with a process ID of one
this is the process ID of the service
inside of the container namespace if we
list the services on the docker host we
will see the same service but with a
different process ID that indicates that
all processes are in fact running on the
same host but separated into their own
containers using namespaces so we
learned that the underlying docker host
as well as the containers share the same
system resources such as CPU and memory
how much of the resources are dedicated
to the host and the containers and how
does docker manage and share the
resources between the containers by
default there is no restriction as to
how much of a resource a container can
use and hence a container may end up
utilizing all of the resources on the
underlying host but there is a way to
restrict the amount of CPU or memory a
container can use docker uses three
groups or control groups to restrict the
amount of hardware resources allocated
to each container this can be done by
providing the - - CPUs option to the
docker run command providing a value of
0.5 will ensure that the container does
not take up more than 50% of the host
CPU at any given time the same goes with
memory setting a value of hundred M to
the - - memory option limits the amount
of memory the container can use to a
hundred megabytes if you are interested
in reading more on this topic refer to
the links I posted in
the reference page that's it for now on
docker engine earlier in this course we
learned that containers share the
underlying OS kernel and as a result we
cannot have a Windows container running
on Linux host or vice versa we need to
keep this in mind while going through
this lecture as it's very important
concept and most beginners tend to have
an issue with it so what are the options
available for docker on Windows there
are two options available
the first one is dock or on Windows
using docker toolbox and the second one
is the docker desktop for Windows option
we will look at each of these now let's
take a look at the first option docker
toolbox this was the original support
for docker on Windows imagine that you
have a Windows laptop and no access to
any Linux system whatsoever but you
would like to try docker you don't have
access to a Linux system in the lab or
in the cloud what would you do what I
did was to install a virtualization
software on my Windows system like
Oracle VirtualBox or VMware Workstation
and deploy a Linux VM on it such as
Ubuntu or Debian then install docker on
the Linux VM and then play around with
it this is what the first option really
does it doesn't really have anything
much to do with Windows you cannot
create Windows based docker images or
run Windows based docker containers you
obviously cannot run Linux container
directly on Windows either you're just
working with docker on a Linux virtual
machine on a Windows host docker
however provides us with a set of tools
to make this easy which is called as the
docker toolbox the docker toolbox
contains a set of tools like Oracle
VirtualBox docker engine docker machine
docker compose and a user interface
called CAD Matic this will help you get
started by simply downloading and
running the docker toolbox executable I
will install virtualbox deploy a
lightweight VM called boot to docker
which has docker
it already so that you are all set to
start with docker easily and with within
a short period of time
now what about requirements you must
ensure that your operating system is
64-bit Windows 7 or higher and that the
virtualization is enabled on the system
now remember docker to box is a legacy
solution for older Windows systems that
do not meet requirements for the newer
docker for Windows option the second
option is the NewYork an option called
docker Desktop for Windows in the
previous option we saw that we had
Oracle VirtualBox installed on Windows
and then a Linux system and then docker
on that Linux system now with docker for
Windows we take out Oracle VirtualBox
and use the native virtualization
technology available with Windows called
Microsoft hyper-v during the
installation process for docker for
Windows it will still automatically
create a Linux system underneath but
this time it is created on the Microsoft
hyper-v instead of Oracle VirtualBox and
have docker running on that system
because of this dependency on hyper-v
this option is only supported for
Windows 10 enterprise or professional
Edition and on Windows Server 2016
because both these operating systems
come with hyper-v support by default now
here is the most important point so far
whatever we have been discussing with
Dockers support for Windows it is
strictly for Linux containers Linux
applications packaged into Linux docker
images we're not talking about Windows
applications or Windows images or
Windows containers both the options we
just discussed will help you run a Linux
container on a Windows host with Windows
Server 2016 Microsoft announced support
for Windows containers for the first
time you can now packaged applications
Windows applications into Windows docker
containers and run them on Windows
chopper host using docker desktop for
Windows when you install docker desktop
for Windows the default option is to
work with Linux containers but if you
would like to run Windows containers
then you must explicitly configure
docker
windows to switch to using windows
containers in early 2016
Microsoft announced windows containers
then you could create Windows based
images and run Windows containers on a
Windows server just like how you would
run Linux containers on a Linux system
now you can create windows images
container as your applications and share
them through the docker store as well
unlike in Linux there are two types of
containers in Windows the first one is a
Windows Server container which works
exactly like Linux containers where the
OS kernel is shared with the underlying
operating system to allow better
security boundary between containers and
to a lot of kernels with different
versions and configurations to coexist
the second option was introduced known
as the hyper-v isolation with hyper-v
isolation each container is run within a
highly optimized virtual machine
guaranteeing complete kernel isolation
between the containers and the
underlying host now while in the Linux
world you had a number of base images
for a Linux system such as ubuntu debian
fedora alpine etc if you remember that
that is what you specify the beginning
of the docker file in the windows world
we have two options the Windows server
core and nano server a nano server is a
headless deployment option for Windows
Server which runs at a fraction of size
of the full operating system you can
think of this like the Alpine image in
Linux the windows server core though is
not as lightweight as you might expect
it to be finally Windows containers are
supported on Windows Server 2016 nano
server and windows 10 professional and
Enterprise Edition remember on Windows
10 professional and Enterprise Edition
only supports hyper-v isolated
containers meaning as we just discussed
every container deployed is deployed on
a highly optimized virtual machine well
that's it about docker on windows now
before I finish I want to point out one
important fact we saw two ways of
running a docker container using
VirtualBox or hyper
but remember VirtualBox and hyper-v
cannot coexist on the same Windows host
so if you started off with docker
toolbox with VirtualBox and if you plan
to migrate to hyper-v remember you
cannot have both solutions at the same
time there is a migration and guide
available on docker documentation page
on how to migrate from Marshall box to
hyper wait that's it for now thank you
and I will see you in the next lecture
[Music]
we now look at docker on Mac docker on
Mac is similar to docker on Windows
there are two options to get started
docker on Mac using docker toolbox or
docker Desktop for Mac option let's look
at the first option docker toolbox this
was the original support for docker on
Mac it is darker on a Linux VM created
using VirtualBox on Mac as with Windows
it has nothing to do with Mac
applications or Mac based images or Mac
containers it purely runs Linux
containers on a Mac OS dollar toolbox
contains a set of tools like Oracle
VirtualBox docker and Jane docker
machine docker compose and a user
interface called CAD Matic when you
download and install the docker toolbox
executable it installs
VirtualBox deploys lightweight VM called
boot a docker which has darker running
in it already
this requires Mac OS 10.8 or newer the
second option is the newer option called
docker Desktop for Mac with docker
Desktop for Mac we take out or
commercial box and use hyper cat
virtualization technology during the
installation process for docker for Mac
it will still automatically create a
Linux system underneath but this time it
is created on hyper kit instead of
Oracle VirtualBox and have docker
running on that system
this requires Mac OS Sierra 10.12 or
newer and Martin and the Mac hardware
must be 2010 or newer model finally
remember that all of this is to be able
to run the Linux container on Mac as of
this recording there are no Mac based
images or containers well that
with docker on Mac for now we will now
try to understand what container
orchestration is so far in this course
we've seen that with docker you can run
a single instance of the application
with a simple docker run command in this
case to run a node.js based application
you're on the docker run nodejs command
but that's just one instance of your
application on one docker host what
happens when the number of users
increase and that instance is no longer
able to handle the load you deploy
additional instance of your application
by running the docker run command
multiple times so that's something you
have to do yourself you have to keep a
close watch on the load and performance
of your application and deploy
additional instances yourself and not
just that you have to keep a close watch
on the health of these applications and
if a container was to fail you should be
able to detect that and run the docker
run command again to deploy another
instance of that application what about
the health of the docker host itself
what if the host crashes and is
inaccessible the containers hosted on
that host become inaccessible too so
what do you do in order to solve these
issues you will need a dedicated
engineer who can sit and monitor the
state performance and health of the
containers and take necessary actions to
remediate the situation but when you
have large applications deployed with
tens of thousands of containers that's
that's not a practical approach so you
can build your own scripts and and that
will help you tackle these issues to
some extent container orchestration is
just a solution for that it is a
solution that consists of a set of tools
and scripts that can help host
containers in a production environment
typically a container orchestration
solution consists of multiple docker
hosts that can host containers that way
even if one fails the application is
still accessible through the others the
container orchestration solution is
allows you to deploy hundreds or
thousands of instances of your
application with a single command this
is a command used for docker swarm we'll
look at the command itself in a bit
some orchestration solutions can help
you automatically scale up the number of
instances when users increase and scale
down the number of instances when the
demand decreases some solutions can even
help you in automatically adding
additional hosts to support the user
load and not just clustering and scaling
the container orchestration solutions
also provide support for advanced
networking between these containers
across different hosts as well as load
balancing user requests across different
house they also provide support for
sharing storage between the house as
well as support for configuration
management and security within the
cluster there are multiple container
orchestration solutions available today
docker has docker swamp kubernetes from
Google and mezzo mezz from Paget while
docker swamp is really easy to set up
and get started it lacks some of the
advanced auto scaling features required
for complex production grade
applications mezzos on the other hand is
quite difficult to set up and get
started
but supports many advanced features
kubernetes arguably the most popular of
it all is a bit difficult to set up and
get started but provides a lot of
options to customize deployments and has
support for many different vendors
kubernetes is now supported on all
public cloud service providers like GCP
azure and AWS and the kubernetes project
is one of the top-ranked projects on
github in upcoming lectures we will take
a quick look at docker swamp and
kubernetes
[Music]
we will now get a quick introduction to
docker swarm docker swarm has a lot of
concepts to cover and requires its own
course but we will try to take a quick
look at some of the basic details so you
can get a brief idea on what it is with
docker swarm you could now combine
multiple docker machines together into a
single cluster docker swarm will take
care of distributing your services or
your application instances into separate
hosts for high availability and for load
balancing across different systems and
hardware to set up a docker swamp you
must first have hosts or multiple hosts
with docker installed on them then you
must designate one host to be the
manager or the master or the swamp
manager as it is called and others as
slaves or workers once you're done with
that run the docker swarm init command
on the swarm manager and that will
initialize the swamp manager the output
will also provide the command to be run
on the workers so copy the command and
run it on the worker nodes to join the
manager after joining the swamp the
workers are also referred to as nodes
and you're now ready to create services
and deploy them on the swamp cluster so
let's get into some more details as you
already know to run an instance of my
web server
I run the docker run command and specify
the name of the image I wish to run this
creates a new container instance of my
application and serves my web server now
that we have learned how to create a
swamp cluster how do I utilize my
cluster to run multiple instances of my
web server now one way to do this would
be to run the docker run command on each
worker node but that's not ideal as I
might have to log into each node and run
this command and there there could be
hundreds of nodes I will have to set up
load balancing myself a large monitor
the state of each instance myself and if
instances were to fail I'll have to
restart them myself so it's going to be
an impossible task that is where docker
swarm orchestration consent
dr. Swan Orchestrator does all of this
for us so far we've only set up this one
cluster but we haven't seen
orchestration in action the key
component of suam orchestration is the
Ducker a service
dr. services are one or more instances
of a single application or service that
runs across the song the nodes in the
song cluster for example in this case I
could create a docker service to run
multiple instances of my web server
application across worker nodes in my
swamp cluster for this around the docker
service create command on the manager
node and specify my image name there
which is my web server in this case and
use the option replicas to specify the
number of instances of my web server I
would like to run across the cluster
since I specified 3 replicas and I get 3
instances of my web server distributed
across the different worker nodes
remember the docker service command must
be run on the manager node and not on
the worker node the docker service
create command is similar to the docker
run command in terms of the options
passed such as the - e environment
variable the - key for publishing ports
the network option to attach container
to a network etc well that's a
high-level introduction to dr. Swan
there's a lot more to know such as
configuring multiple managers overlay
networks etc as I mentioned it requires
its own separate course well that's it
for now in the next lecture we will look
at kubernetes at a higher level
[Music]
we will now get a brief introduction to
basic kubernetes concepts again
kubernetes requires its own course well
a few courses at least five but we will
try to get a brief introduction to it
here with docker you were able to run a
single instance of an application using
the docker CLI by running the docker run
command which is grid running an
application has never been so easy
before with kubernetes using the
kubernetes CLI known as cube control you
can run a thousand instance of the same
application with a single command
kubernetes can scale it up to two
thousand with another command kubernetes
can be even configured to do these
automatically so that instances and the
infrastructure itself can scale up and
down based on user load kubernetes can
upgrade these 2000 instances of the
application in a rolling upgrade fashion
one at a time with a single command if
something goes wrong it can help you
roll back these images with a single
command kubernetes can help you test new
features of your application by only
upgrading a percentage of these
instances through a be testing methods
the kubernetes open architecture
provides support for many many different
network and storage vendors any network
or storage brand that you can think of
has a plugin for kubernetes kubernetes
supports a variety of authentication and
authorization mechanisms all major cloud
service providers have native support
for kubernetes so what's the relation
between docker and kubernetes well
kubernetes uses docker host to host
applications in the form of docker
containers well it need not be docker
all the time
kubernetes supports as relatives to
Dockers as well such as rocket or a cryo
but let's take a quick look at the
kubernetes architecture a kubernetes
cluster consists of a set of nodes let
us start with nodes in node is a machine
physical or virtual on which a cobranet
is
Karina's software a set of tools are
installed a node is a worker machine and
that is where containers will be
launched by kubernetes but what if the
node on which the application is running
fails well obviously our application
goes down so you need to have more than
one nodes a cluster is a set of nodes
grouped together this way even if one
node fails you have your application
still accessible from the other nodes
now we have a cluster but who is
responsible for managing this cluster
where's the information about the
members of the cluster stored how are
the nodes monitored when a node fails
how do you move the workload of the
failed nodes to another worker node
that's where the master comes in the
master is a note with the kubernetes
control plane components installed the
master watches over the nodes are in the
cluster and is responsible for the
actual orchestration of containers on
the worker nodes when you install
kubernetes on a system you're actually
installing the following components an
API server and EDD server a cubelet
service contain a runtime engine like
docker and a bunch of controllers and
the scheduler the API server acts as the
front end for kubernetes the users
management devices command line
interfaces all talk to the API server to
interact with the kubernetes cluster
next is the Etsy be a key value store
the Etsy D is a distributed reliable key
value store used by kubernetes to store
all data used to manage the cluster
think of it this way when you have
multiple nodes and multiple masters in
your cluster let CD stores all that
information on all the nodes in the
cluster in a distributed manner and CD
is responsible for implementing a locks
within the cluster to ensure there are
no conflicts between the masters the
scheduler is responsible for
distributing work or containers across
multiple nodes it looks for newly
created containers and assigns them to
notes the controllers are the brain
behind orchestration they're responsible
for noticing and responding when
notes containers or endpoints goes down
the controllers makes decisions to bring
up new containers in such cases the
container runtime is the underlying
software that is used to run containers
in our case it happens to be docker and
finally cubelet is the agent that runs
on each node in the cluster the agent is
responsible for making sure that the
containers are running on the notes as
expected and finally we also need to
learn a little bit about one of the
command-line utilities known as the cube
command-line tool or the cube control
tool or cube cuddle as it is also called
the cube control tool is the kubernetes
CLI which is used to deploy and manage
applications on a convergence cluster to
get cluster related information to get
the status with the nodes in the cluster
and many other things the cube control
run command is used to deploy an
application on the cluster the keep
control cluster info command is used to
view information about the cluster and
the cube control get nodes command is
used to list all the nodes part of the
cluster so to run hundreds of instances
of your application across hundreds of
nodes all I need is a single kubernetes
command like this well that's all we
have for now a quick introduction to
Cornelis and its architecture we
currently have three courses on code
cloud on kubernetes that will take you
from the absolute beginner to a
certified expert so have a look at it
when you get a chance
[Music]
so we're at the end of this beginners
course to docker I hope you had a great
learning experience if so please leave a
comment below if you like my way of
teaching you will love my other courses
hosted on my site at code cloud we have
courses for docker swarm kubernetes
advanced courses on kubernetes
certifications as well as OpenShift we
have courses for automation tools like
Antigo chef and puppet and many more on
the way with it code cloud at
www.calculated.com/support
[Music]